<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629-xhtml.ent">
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" ipr="trust200902" docName="draft-ietf-cose-x509-07" category="info" submissionType="IETF" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 2.24.0 -->
  <front>
    <title abbrev="COSE X.509">CBOR Object Signing and Encryption (COSE): Header parameters for carrying and referencing X.509 certificates</title>
    <author initials="J." surname="Schaad" fullname="Jim Schaad">
      <organization>August Cellars</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ietf@augustcellars.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <area>Security</area>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        The CBOR Signing And Encrypted Message (COSE) structure uses references to keys in general.
        For some algorithms, additional properties are defined which carry parts of keys as needed.
        The COSE Key structure is used for transporting keys outside of COSE messages.
        This document extends the way that keys can be identified and transported by providing attributes that refer to or contain X.509 certificates.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <note removeInRFC="true">
      <name>Contributing to this document</name>
      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please remove this note before publishing -->
      <t>
        The source for this draft is being maintained in GitHub.
        Suggested changes should be submitted as pull requests  at <eref target="https://github.com/cose-wg/X509"/>.
        Instructions are on that page as well.
        Editorial changes can be managed in GitHub, but any substantial issues need to be discussed on the COSE mailing list.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section anchor="introduction">
      <name>Introduction</name>
      <t>
        In the process of writing <xref target="RFC8152"/> the working group discussed X.509 certificates  <xref target="RFC5280"/> ad decided that no use cases wher prestented that showed a need to support certificates.
        Since that time a number of cases have been defined in which X.509 certificate support is necessary, and by implication, applications will need a documented and consistent way to handle such certificates.
        This document defines a set of attributes that will allow applications to transport and refer to X.509 certificates in a consistent manner.
      </t>
      <t>
        <!-- JLS - Robin did you really mean to just refer to version -00? -->
	In some of these cases, a constrained device is being deployed in the context of an existing X.509 PKI: for example, in the 6TiSCH environment <xref target="I-D.richardson-enrollment-roadmap"/>, describes a device enrollment solution that relies on the presence in the device of a factory-installed certificate.
	The <xref target="I-D.selander-ace-cose-ecdhe"/> draft was also written with the idea that long term certificates could be used to provide for authentication of devices, and uses them to establish session keys.
	A third scenario is the use of COSE as the basis for a secure messaging application.
        This scenario assumes the presence of long term keys and a central authentication authority.
	Basing such an application on public key certificates allows it to make use of well established key management disciplines.
      </t>
      <t>
        Example COSE messages for the various header parameters defined below can be found at https://github.com/cose-wg/Examples.
      </t>
      
      <section anchor="requirements-terminology">
        <name>Requirements Terminology</name>
        <!--  NOTE FOR AUTHORS:
             We use the following terms in the document
             
             field - an entry in a CBOR array
             parameter - an element in a CBOR map (as oppose to 'member' which is frequently used in JSON
             label - the key of an element in a CBOR map.   Unless otherwise separated from text, enclose with single quote marks
             value - the value of an element in a CBOR map
        -->
        <t>
          The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>X.509 COSE Header Parameters</name>
      <!-- Robin
      [This section contains a number of uses of "may", "can", "cannot" etc.; should those be reworked for RFC2119 compliance?]
      -->
      <t>
        The use of X.509 certificates allows for an existing trust infrastructure to be used with COSE.
	This includes the full suite of enrollment protocols, trust anchors, trust chaining and revocation checking that have been defined over time by the IETF and other organizations.
	The key structures that have been defined in COSE currently do not support all of these properties although some may be found in COSE Web Tokens (CWT) <xref target="RFC8392"/>.
      </t>
      <t>
	It is not necessarily expected that constrained devices themselves will evaluate and process of X.509 certificates:
        it is perfectly reasonable for a constrained device to be provisioned with a certificate which it can then provide to a relying party - along with a signature or encrypted message - on the assumption that the relying party is not a constrained device, and is capable of performing the required certificate evaluation and processing.
        It is also reasonable that a constrained device would have the hash of a certificate associated with a public key and be configured use a public key for that thumbprint, but without performing the certificate evaluation or even having the entire certificate.        
      </t>
      <t>
        Certificates obtained from any of these methods MUST still be validated.
        This validation can be done according to the PKIX rules in <xref target="RFC5280"/> or by using a different trust structure, such as a trusted certificate distributor for self-signed certificates.
        The PKIX validation includes matching against the trust anchors configured for the application.
        These rules apply to certificates of a chain length of one as well as longer chains.
        If the application cannot establish trust in the certificate, that certificate cannot be used.
      </t>
      <t>
        The header parameters defined in this document are:

      </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>x5bag:</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
	    This header parameter contains a bag of X.509 certificates.
	    The set of certificates in this header parameter is unordered and may contain self-signed certificates.
            The certificate bag can contain certificates which are completely extraneous to the message.
	    (An example of this would be where a signed message is being used to transport a certificate containing a key agreement key.)
	    As the certificates are unordered, the party evaluating the signature will need to be capable of building the certificate path as necessary.
            That party will also have to take into account that the bag may not contain the full set of certificates needed to build any particular chain.
          </t>
          <t>
            The trust mechanism MUST process any certificates in this parameter as untrusted input.
            The presence of a self-signed certificate in the parameter MUST NOT be used as a signal to modify the set of trust anchors.
            As the contents of this header parameter are untrusted input, the header parameter can be in either the protected or unprotected header bucket.
      <!-- Robin
      [Is the point being made here that the header is incidental to any trust processing that is done on the basis of the certificates in the bag?
      If so, I suggest the following text:
      "As the trust mechanisms in operation here do not depend on the header element itself, the header attribute MAY be either protected or unprotected. "]

        JLS:
        Does this read better?
      -->
          </t>
          <t>
            This header parameter allows for a single X.509 certificate or a bag of X.509 certificates to be carried in the message.
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
                If a single certificate is conveyed, it is placed in a CBOR bstr.
              </li>
            <li>
                If multiple certificates are conveyed, a CBOR array of bstrs is used, with each certificate being in its own bstr.
              </li>
          </ul>
        </dd>
        <dt>x5chain:</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
	    This header parameter contains an ordered array of X.509 certificates.
	    The certificates are to be ordered starting with the certificate containing the end-entity key followed by the certificate which signed it and so on.
	    There is no requirement for the entire chain to be present in the element if there is reason to believe that the relying party already has, or can locate the missing certificates.
            This means that the relying party is still required to do path building, but that a candidate path is proposed in this attribute.
          </t>
          <t>
      <!-- Robin
      [Is the point being made here that the header is incidental to any trust processing that is done on the basis of the certificates in the bag?
      If so, I suggest the following text:
      "As the trust mechanisms in operation here do not depend on the header element itself, the header attribute MAY be either protected or unprotected. "]
      -->
            The trust mechanism MUST process any certificates in this parameter as untrusted input.
            The presence of a self-signed certificate in the parameter MUST NOT be used as a signal to modify the set of trust anchors.
            As the contents of this header parameter are untrusted input, the header parameter can be in either the protected or unprotected header bucket.
          </t>
          <t>
            This header parameter allows for a single X.509 certificate or a chain of X.509 certificates to be carried in the message.
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>
                If a single certificate is conveyed, it is placed in a CBOR bstr.
              </li>
            <li>
                If multiple certificates are conveyed, a CBOR array of bstrs is used, with each certificate being in its own bstr.
              </li>
          </ul>
        </dd>
        <dt>x5t:</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            This header parameter provides the ability to identify an X.509 certificate by a hash value.
            The attribute is an array of two elements.
            The first element is an algorithm identifier which is an integer or a string containing the hash algorithm identifier.
            The algorithm is registered in the "COSE Algorithms" registry
            The second element is a binary string containing the hash value.
          </t>
          <t>
	    As this header parameter does not provide any trust, the header parameter can be in either a protected or unprotected header bucket.
          </t>
          <t>
            For interoperability, applications which use this header parameter MUST support the hash algorithm 'SHA-256', but can use other hash algorithms.
          </t>
          <t>RFC Editor please remove the following paragraphs:</t>
          <t>
            During AD review, a question was raised about how effective the previous statement is in terms of dealing with a MTI algorithm.
            There needs to be some type of arrangement between the parties to agree that a specific hash algorithm is going to be used in computing the thumbprint.
              Making it a MUST use would make that true, but it then means that agility is going to be very difficult.
          </t>
          <t>
            The worry is that while SHA-256 may be mandatory, if a sender supports SHA-256 but only sends SHA-512 then the recipient which only does SHA-256 would not be able to use the thumbprint.
            In that case both applications would conform to the specification, but still not be able to inter-operate.
          </t>
        </dd>
        <dt>x5u:</dt>
        <dd>
          <t>
            This header parameter provides the ability to identify an X.509 certificate by a URI <xref target="RFC3986"/>.
            The referenced resource can be any of the following media types:
          </t>
          <ul spacing="normal">
            <li>application/pkix-cert <xref target="RFC2585"/></li>
            <li>application/pkcs7-mime; smime-type="certs-only" <xref target="RFC8551"/></li>
            <!--              <t>application/pem-certificate-chain <xref target="I-D.ietf-acme-acme"/></t> -->
          </ul>
          <t>
	    As this header parameter implies a trust relationship, the attribute MUST be in the protected attribute bucket.
          </t>
          <t>
            The URI provided MUST provide integrity protection and server authentication.
            For example, an HTTP or CoAP GET request to retrieve a certificate MUST use TLS <xref target="RFC8446"/> or DTLS <xref target="I-D.ietf-tls-dtls13"/>.
            If the certificate does not chain to an existing trust anchor, the certificate MUST NOT be trusted unless the server is configured as trusted to provide new trust anchors.
            In particular, self-signed certificates MUST NOT be trusted without an out-of-band confirmation.
          </t>
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <t>
	The header parameters are used in the following locations:
      </t>
      <ul spacing="normal">
        <li>
	    COSE_Signature and COSE_Sign1 objects: in these objects they identify the certificate to be used for validating the signature.
	  </li>
        <li>
            COSE_recipient objects: in this location they identify the certificate for the recipient of the message.
          </li>
      </ul>
      <table anchor="Tags" align="center">
        <name>X.509 COSE Header Parameters</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Name</th>
            <th align="left">Label</th>
            <th align="left">Value Type</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5bag</td>
            <td align="left">TBD4</td>
            <td align="left">COSE_X509</td>
            <td align="left">An unordered bag of X.509 certificates</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5chain</td>
            <td align="left">TBD3</td>
            <td align="left">COSE_X509</td>
            <td align="left">An ordered chain of X.509 certificates</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5t</td>
            <td align="left">TBD1</td>
            <td align="left">COSE_CertHash</td>
            <td align="left">Hash of an X.509 certificate</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5u</td>
            <td align="left">TBD2</td>
            <td align="left">uri</td>
            <td align="left">URI pointing to an X.509 certificate</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <t>
        Below is an equivalent CDDL <xref target="RFC8610"/> description of the text above.
      </t>
      <artwork type="CDDL" name="" align="left" alt=""><![CDATA[
COSE_X509 = bstr / [ 2*certs: bstr ]
COSE_CertHash = [ hashAlg: (int / tstr), hashValue: bstr ]
]]></artwork>
    </section>
    <section>
      <name>X.509 certificates and static-static ECDH</name>
      <t>
        The header parameters defined in the previous section are used to identify the recipient certificates for the ECDH key agreement algorithms.
        In this section we define the algorithm specific parameters that are used for identifying or transporting the sender's key for static-static key agreement algorithms.
      </t>
      <t>
        These attributes are defined analogously to those in the previous section.
        There is no definition for the certificate bag, as the same attribute would be used for both the sender and recipient certificates.
        <!-- Robin
        [I think this needs a little more explanation, for example (if correct):
        "For static-static ECDH key agreement, the message MUST use one of the following 3 header attributes;
        the x5bag attribute is not valid in this use case, because... ?x5bag implies that the sender and recipient may use different attributes?."
        
        JLS
        No that is not correct.  If doing static-static, then there are two different certificates that need to be identified, that of the sender
        and that of the recipient.  The recipient certificate would be identified by the x5c or x5t properties.  The sender certificate
        would be defined by one of these certificates.  If you used x5t and x5t-sender, but include both certificates in the bag of certificates.
        Normally only the sender certificates would be included as it is assumed that the recipient can identify its certificate without being
        given the actual certificate.
        
        How much of this needs to be added above?
        -->

      </t>
      <dl newline="false" spacing="normal">
        <dt>x5chain-sender:</dt>
        <dd>
            This header parameter contains the chain of certificates starting with the sender's key exchange certificate.
            The structure is the same as 'x5chain'.
          </dd>
        <dt>x5t-sender:</dt>
        <dd>
            This header parameter contains the hash value for the sender's key exchange certificate.
            The structure is the same as 'x5t'.
          </dd>
        <dt>x5u-sender:</dt>
        <dd>
            This header parameter contains a URI for the sender's key exchange certificate.
            The structure and processing are the same as 'x5u'.
          </dd>
      </dl>
      <table anchor="Tags2" align="center">
        <name>Static ECDH Algorithm Values</name>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th align="left">Name</th>
            <th align="left">Label</th>
            <th align="left">Type</th>
            <th align="left">Algorithm</th>
            <th align="left">Description</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5t-sender</td>
            <td align="left">TBD</td>
            <td align="left">COSE_CertHash</td>
            <td align="left">ECDH-SS+HKDF-256, ECDH-SS+HKDF-512, ECDH-SS+A128KW, ECDH-SS+AES192KW, ECDH-SS+AES256KW</td>
            <td align="left">Thumbprint for the senders X.509 certificate</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5u-sender</td>
            <td align="left">TBD</td>
            <td align="left">uri</td>
            <td align="left">ECDH-SS+HKDF-256, ECDH-SS+HKDF-512, ECDH-SS+A128KW, ECDH-SS+AES192KW, ECDH-SS+AES256KW</td>
            <td align="left">URI for the senders X.509 certificate</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td align="left">x5chain-sender</td>
            <td align="left">TBD</td>
            <td align="left">COSE_X509</td>
            <td align="left">ECDH-SS+HKDF-256, ECDH-SS+HKDF-512, ECDH-SS+A128KW, ECDH-SS+AES192KW, ECDH-SS+AES256KW</td>
            <td align="left">static key X.509 certificate chain</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana-considerations">
      <name>IANA Considerations</name>
      <section anchor="cose-header-key-table">
        <name>COSE Header Parameter Registry</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the new COSE Header parameters in <xref target="Tags"/> in the "COSE Header Parameters" registry.
          The "Value Registry" field is empty for all of the items.
          For each item, the 'Reference' field points to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section>
        <name>COSE Header Algorithm Parameter Registry</name>
        <t>
          IANA is requested to register the new COSE Header Algorithm parameters in <xref target="Tags2"/> in the "COSE Header Algorithm Parameters" registry.
          For each item, the 'Reference' field points to this document.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security-considerations">
      <name>Security Considerations</name>
      <t>
        Establishing trust in a certificate is a vital part of processing.
        A major component of establishing trust is determining what the set of trust anchors are for the process.
        A new self-signed certificate appearing on the client cannot be a trigger to modify the set of trust anchors, because a well defined trust-establishment process is required.
        One common way for a new trust anchor to be added (or removed) from a device is by doing a new firmware upgrade.
        <!-- Robin
        [Is this true, and if so, does it follow from the preceding statements, or is it a discrete assertion?
        It's not clear to me that adding new trust anchors to constrained devices is the only relevant use case here,
        or that it is the only instance of establishing trust in a certificate.
        Traversing a certificate chain or issuing an OCSP request may be other instances.]

        JLS
        I was trying to deal just with trust anchors - so I have modified the text to reflect that.
        -->
      </t>

      <t>
        In constrained systems, there is a trade-off between the order of checking the signature and checking the certificate for validity.
        Validating certificates can require that network resources be accessed in order to get revocation information or retrieve certificates during path building.
        The resulting network access can consume power and network bandwidth.
        On the other hand, an oracle can potentially be built based on detecting the network resources which is only done if the signature validation passes.
        In any event, both the signature and certificate validation MUST be completed successfully before acting on any requests.
      </t>
      
      <t>
        Before using the key in a certificate, the key MUST be checked against the algorithm to be used and any algorithm specific checks need to be made.
        These checks can include validating that points are on curves for elliptical curve algorithms, and that sizes of RSA keys are of an acceptable size.
        The use of unvalidated keys can lead either to loss of security or excessive consumption of resources (for example using a 200K RSA key).
        
        <!-- Robin
        Two questions:
        (1) are there any other important checks that should be noted here, or is the  COSE algs document the authoritative guide?
        (2) how does use of unvalidated keys lead to excessive resource consumption?
        
        (1) The COSE algorithm draft(s) have the be the authoritative guides because the set is going to be algorithm specific.
        (2) The easiest example would be an RSA key which is 16K bits long.  Doing the match on this will take a significantly longer amount of time
            and use a significantly amount of memory than what would be used by a 2048-bit RSA key.
      -->
      </t>
      
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references xml:base="http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/">
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative References</name>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <!-- <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.I-D.ietf-cose-rfc8152bis-struct.xml"/>-->
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative References</name>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.8446.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-tls-dtls13.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.8551.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.2585.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml3/reference.I-D.selander-ace-cose-ecdhe.xml"/>
        <!-- <?rfc include="bibxml/reference.RFC.7468.xml" ?> PEM -->
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.8392.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.8152.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.8610.xml"/>
        <!-- <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.I-D.ietf-acme-acme.xml"/> -->
        <xi:include href="bibxml/reference.RFC.3986.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="bibxml3/reference.I-D.richardson-enrollment-roadmap.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
